Finding Aid for Department of Otolaryngology (University of Michigan) publications, 1988-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Otolaryngology (University of Michigan) publications 1988-1991
University of Michigan. Department of Otolaryngology,
0.2 linear feet
0358 Bimu C46 2
Includes an annual report entitled, Twenty-Fifth Anniversary annual Report: 1963-1988, as well as bibliographies and brochures of the Kresge Hearing Research Institute.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accessioned from Donor no. 2289, materials continue to be periodically received.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publicatons are open without restriction.
The study of ears, nose and throat at the University of Michigan was originally linked with ophthalmology. George Edward Rothingham served as Professor of Materia Medica and Ophthalmology from 1872 to 1889, and Flemming Carrow was Professor of Ophthalmic and Aural Surgery, Laryngology, and Clinical Ophthalmology from 1889 to 1904. But the Department of Otolarygology began to take shape with the appointment of Roy Bishop Canfield in 1904 as Clinical Professor of the Diseases of the Ear, Nose, and Throat, then as Professor of Otolaryngology in 1905.
Dr. Canfield remained the only professor in the department for thirteen years, and he distinguished the position with his innovative and successful surgery techniques. Albert Carl Furstenberg was appointed Acting Assistant Professor of Otolaryngology in 1918, and eventually took over the chair at the death of Dr. Canfield in 1932 in an automobile accident.
In 1959, Furstenberg resigned from the chair and was succeeded by James Hoyt Maxwell, who died in 1960. Walter Paxton Work took over in 1961. From 1962/63 through the mid-1990's, the department used the name Otorhinolaryngology. Dr. Work retired, and was replaced by Charles J. Krause in 1977. In 1992, after Krause was appointed Senior Associate Dean of the Medical School, Gregory Wolf took over the chair.
Kresge Hearing Research Institute
In 1959, a committee composed of members of the medical school faculty--including Merle Lawrence and Brian McCabe of the Department of Otolaryngology--was formed to work with the Kresge Foundation to form a hearing research institute. The committee submitted a proposal to the foundation, and received $1,750,000 for the construction of the Kresge Hearing Research Institute.
Merle Lawrence was appointed the Director of the Institute in 1961, and the new building was dedicated in 1963. At this time, the Regents' By-Laws created an Advisory Committee of the Faculty to govern the Institute. However, the Advisory Committee was composed of the chairmen of several other medical departments besides Otorhinolaryngology, and their outside interests prevented this organization from being practical. The Institute was made the research section of the Department of Otorhinolaryngology, and in 1976, the Regents' By-Laws were changed to reflect this structure.
Lawrence retired to Professor Emeritus status in 1984, and Josef Miller became Director of the KHRI. He gave up the position in 1998.
The Department of Otolaryngology Publications contains one series: Sub-Unit Publications. In this series, the Kresge Hearing Research Institute is represented by its Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Annual Report from 1988, a bibliography from 1989/90, and several brochures. The series also includes invitations from the Communication Disorders Clinic.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Otolaryngology.; University of Michigan. Kresge Hearing Research Institute.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Kresge Hearing Research Institute.
Genre Terms:
Annual reports.; Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Kresge Hearing Research Institute
    - Annual Reports
      - 1967/1968 (Box 1)
      - 1973/1974 (Box 1)
      - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary Annual Report: 1963-1988, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies
      - Research in Progress, 1989/90 (Box 1)
    - Brochures
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - Exploring the World of Sound: The Communication Disorders Center, ca. 1988 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Progress Report, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Communication Disorders Center
    - Invitations, 1989 (Box 1)